Guide to the National Cherry Blossom Festival records, 1909-2000 MS2046
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Cherry Blossom Festival records
1909-2000
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Cherry Blossom Festival (Washington, D.C.)
MS2046
3.5 Linear Feet
Collection tells the story of the beginning of the National Cherry Blossom Festival mostly through letters and newspaper articles. In addition, the official festival programs relate the different activities and volunteers. The collection has seven series arranged by type of material.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Paul Skrabut, a festival volunteer, donated this collection of material related to the National Cherry Blossom Festival, its history and the operations by the National Cherry Blossom Festival, Inc.
Historical or Biographical Note
The idea to plant cherry trees along the Tidal Basin in Potomac Park came from Helen Herron Taft, wife of President Taft. Hearing about the planned planting, the Japanese government donated 3,000 cherry blossom trees to the United States. At the March 27, 1912 planting ceremony, Mrs. Taft planted the first tree followed by Viscountess Chinda, wife of the Japanese Ambassador. The first celebration of this event came in 1927, when school children reenacted the initial planting. In 1935, many local civic groups combined to sponsor a three-day event to commemorate the Japanese gift. Since this first event, the National Cherry Blossom Festival has grown in popularity. The festival is two weeks long and includes many events such as a formal ball, pageant, parade, concert, and a ten-mile road race. In 1985 the National Cherry Blossom Festival coordinating group became a not-for-profit umbrella organization whose stated purpose is to "... coordinate, promote, and provide for public participation in the Festival." The members of the organization are volunteers from local businesses, civic groups, the D.C. government, and the National Park Service.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection tells the story of the beginning of the Festival mostly through letters and newspaper articles. In addition, the official festival programs relate the different activities and volunteers. The collection has seven series arranged by type of material. Due to its completeness, the most useful series in the collection is the early history. The series includes photocopies of the first letters written in 1909 from the Superintendent of Public Buildings and Grounds and Washington Monument to the Landscape Gardener of Greenhouses, and Monument Grounds. These letters and others in the folder discuss the original donation in 1909 and a second donation in 1912. Newspaper articles and official festival programs add to this history. Although not complete, the collection does includes the type of material one would expect to find in a collection maintained by a festival volunteer, especially a volunteer who at times held various positions of authority. There are programs, information about advertisement costs, by-laws of the NCBF records of organizations affiliated with the events, and photographs of festival activities. The collection covers the years 1909-2002. It is 9 boxes and approximately 3.5 linear ft.
Collection Organization
Organized into eight series: Administration files, Affiliate ceremonies, Affiliate organizations, Graphics, Histories, Publications, Videotapes, and Miscellaneous.
Washington (D.C.); Tidal Basin (Washington, D.C.); Photographs
- Administration files, 1987-2000; MS2046 Series 1; 1 Linear foot
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains material such as correspondence, by-laws, press releases, and budget reports. All of these documents are the type one would expect to find in a collection of an organization especially when the donor is a volunteer who often held positions of authority within the organization. The series is not a complete record of the workings of the National Cherry Blossom Festival, Inc, but will provide information about the organization in general such as the by-laws and about specific activities such as the disagreement in the late 1990s between the NCBF and the National Conference of State Societies.
  - Acknowledgements, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Advertisements, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Advertisement costs, 1986-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Board, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agreements and Disclosures, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Art of Sushi, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Budget Reports, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - By-laws, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cherry Blossom Princess Presentation Ball, 1968-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Officials, 1983-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Daytime events, 1984-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Daytime events, 1996-2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - E-mails, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Evening events invitations and programs, 1982-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Japanese Performances, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Japanese Travel Guide and Map, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Japan-U.S. Travel, 1988-2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1995-2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NCBF vs. NCSS National Conference of State Societies, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Odyssey Cruises, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Press Releases, 1989-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Public Laws, 1952-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tax Information, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Trademark Office, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kathleen Arnold, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - William Barbee, Board Member, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cecil Corry, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hiromu Honma, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hiroko Ikeda Papers, Board Member, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Glenn Mahone, NCSS member, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Shigeo Mori, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Niroko Okamoto, Board Member, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kinjiro Omae, Shinju Pearl member, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Paul Skrabut, Board Member, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Drew Von Berger, Board Member, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - John Warner, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jackie Wolfe, Board Member, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Affiliate ceremonies, 1999; MS2046 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series has information about the Flowering Dogwood Ceremony and various cherry blossom festivals around the country and the world including Hawaii, California, and Japan. In 1915, as a thank you for the cherry tree gift, the United States gave Japan a gift of dogwood trees. The material in the folder has information about the 1999 Flowering Dogwood Ceremony during which a dogwood tree was planted at the site of President Taft's grave in Arlington National Cemetery.
  - Flowering Dogwood Ceremony, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hawaii, Japan and California Cherry Blossom Festivals, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Affiliate organizations, 1995-2000; MS2046 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes information about many organizations that have participated in some way with the National Cherry Blossom Festival. For example, the National Conference of State Societies sponsors the Cherry Blossom Princess Program.
  - Affiliates Organization Arakawa River, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Conference of State Societies (NCSS), 1986-1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - NCSS By-laws, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pearlessesnce, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sa Ku Ra, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sapporo, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Shinju Pearl list of directors, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Touristart.com, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Graphics, undated; MS2046 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  The collection has a significant number of images of various activities held during the festival. Most of the images are not identified, although a year is sometimes provided. The use of the festival programs will assist in the identification of some people in the images.
  - Photograph Album, partial identification, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photograph Album, partial identification, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Album, partial identification, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photograph Album, unidentified negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Phillips Sushi Demonstration, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Histories, 1909-2000; MS2046 Series 5; 0.25 Linear feet
  The series has an early history of the cherry blossom donation and the beginnings of the festival. The information is found in photocopies of original correspondence and newspaper articles. The newspaper articles are in English and Japanese.
  - Cherry Blossom history, 1909-1912 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Historic Press Accounts, 1910-1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Articles, (English), 1984-2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Articles, (Japanese), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Reports, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Program copies, 1941-1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Tree Background, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Publications, 1968-2002; MS2046 Series 6; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series has programs for 1968 and 1977 and from 1984-2002. Some of the programs are from the NCBF and some from the National Conference of State Societies. The program includes information about volunteers, Festival personalities, and events. The programs include lists of members of the Board of Directors, Parade Committee, Festival Committee, and the Cherry Blossom Princesses.
  - Festival Programs, 1968-1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Festival Programs, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Festival Programs, 1993-1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Festival Programs, 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Festival Programs, 1999-2002 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Japan Now, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Videotapes, 1988-1992; MS2046 Series 7; 0.25 Linear feet
  The series includes seven VHS tapes and four 45rpm record albums.
  - 3 VHS tapes with Japanese labels, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - VHS Cherry Blossom Festival, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - VHS Cherry Blossom Festival April, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - VHS Cherry Blossom Festival April 3-9, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 4 Record Albums 45s all with Japanese labels, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1985-2001; MS2046 Series 8; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series is primarily comprised of documents in Japanese.
  - Artwork, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Japanese, 1985-1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Japanese Documents, 1996-2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Japanese Documents, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Large print with Japanese writing, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)